Inventory of the Stasys Silingas papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Stasys Silingas papers
1905-2008
2007C56
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, identification documents, printed matter, miscellany, and photographs, relating mainly to imprisonment of Stasys Silingas in Siberia after 1940.
Silingas, Stasys, 1885-1962
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
Born in Vilnius on November 11, 1885, Baron Stasys Silingas, a Lithuanian lawyer and statesman, was a significant figure in the history of Lithuania's independence.
He graduated from Moscow University in 1912 with a degree in law, and later became one of the founding fathers of Lithuania's Independence from 1918 to 1938. Silingas served first as vice-president and then, in 1919, as president of the Council of Lithuania after the independence of Lithuania was proclaimed on February 16, 1918. Between World War I and World War II he was twice minister of justice, from 1926 to 1928, and from 1934 to 1938. From 1920 to 1926 he was director of the Fine Art association. He also served as vice-chancellor of the Order of Vytautas the Great.
His lifelong interest in the arts led him to become a seminal force in the revival of a flowering Lithuanian art, literature, culture, and nationhood. Aside from assembling a large collection of art himself, he also cofounded the M. K. Èiurlionis Art Museum in Kaunas.
Among his other accomplishments, he drafted the Constitution of Lithuania which was adopted in 1938 and organized the National Guard which successfully repelled an attempted Russian invasion in 1918, during the Lithuanian Wars of Independence. In 1934 he was named Minister of Justice a second time serving until 1938 at which time he withdrew from public life after delivering his "Testament to Lithuania" speech before a convention of the National Guard.
He married Emilija Bytautaitë who was the sister of his closest friend Ramûnas Bytautas, a philosopher. He and Emilija had nine daughters. When he retired from public life in 1938, he moved with his family to Misiûnai, part of an old estate which he had purchased in 1925.
On June 14, 1941, the Soviets arrested him, his wife Emilija, and daughter Raminta. They were separated before being deported to Siberia, where his wife and daughter both died of disease within a couple of years. Ðilingas learned of their location only after Emilija's death, and he never saw any of his family again. He spent over 20 years in exile: in camps and prisons of Siberia, and 7 years incarcerated at an Invalid Home in the Ukrainian SSR. Finally allowed to write letters in 1956, he was able to communicate for the first time with his surviving daughters who now lived in the United States, Australia, and Canada, and with former colleagues who had been allowed to return to the Lithuanian SSR. His voluminous letters are philosophical, scholarly, and historical and reveal some details of his life in exile.
Allowed to return to the Lithuanian SSR only in 1961, he died at Kelmë within a year, on November 13, 1962.
Source: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stasys_Silingas
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, identification documents, printed matter, miscellany, and photographs, relating mainly to imprisonment of Stasys Silingas in Siberia after 1940.
Lithuania--History.; Statesmen--Lithuania.
- Biographical file, 1885-1962
  - General (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Family history (Box-folder 1: 2)
- KGB file on Silingas (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Speeches, "Testament to Lithuania", 1939 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Correspondence
  - To daughters, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Laima, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Daiva, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Galinda, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Rusne, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Danguole, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Vingra, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Saule, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Family, 1956 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Identification papers for Laima Silingas, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Politcal cartoons, 1922 (Box-folder 1: 14)
- Misunai estate maps (Box-folder 1: 15)
- Photo files (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Displaced persons camp, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Exile, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Early years, 1905-1920 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Government, 1926-1928 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Professional life, 1936-1938 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - School photo (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Life in Misiunai, 1924-1938 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Daughters, circa 1920-1940 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Family (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Wedding, 1937 (Box-folder 1: 25)
- Bookmarks (Box-folder 1: 26)
- "Genesis of a Nation's Songs" (Box-folder 1: 27)
- Lietuvai Sibire, 1981 (Box-folder 1: 28-29)
- Nepriklausomos Lietuvos Valstybes Atkurimas, 1917-1922 (Box-folder 1: 30)
- Rest of collection yet to be described (Box 2-3)